A Guide to the Thomas Wolfe Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6348-e
Thomas Wolfe Collection 1926-1950
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6348-e
28 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 Jul 8
Item Listing
- Manuscript
  - Notes and drawing by Thomas Wolfe, AMs, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Thomas Wolfe, Hotel Russell, London, to William Cocke, Oxford, 1926 Nov 28; ALS, 8 p. w/env
    [Departs for Paris soon; longs for light, sounds, food, pretty legs, and faces without hostility of Paris; comments on Cocke's life in Oxford; mentions Cocke's intelligence and adaptability; thanks him for the good time he had in Oxford; hopes Cocke will write him in Paris; hopes the Oxford sun will eventually get out.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Antwerp, Belgium, to Aline Bernstein, New York City, 1926 Sep 27; APCS, 1 p.
    [Says he will return to London the following day; comments on the great, vulgar Flemish paintings in the local museum.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Pall Mall, London, to Herbert S[herman], [ London], [1926]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Lives temporarily in a flat in Pall Mall; uses a doctor's telephone outside of office hours, which are 2-5 p. m.; says that Herbert's letter was forwarded from Paris; states that he is hard at work and does not go out, but would like to meet with Herbert; refers to Jean.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, New York, to [ Francis Hayes], 1930 Feb 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Appreciates letter in praise of [
    Look Homeward, Angel
    ]; says he received the letter after a delay as he has stopped teaching at [ New York University].]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Montreaux, Switzerland, to Melville Cane, [ New York], 1930 Jul 22; ALS, 6 p.
    [Responds to note; describes hotel gardens, mountains, casino; says he needs solitude, but hates it; states he has begun a book which he feels will be fine if he can write it the way he has it inside him; mentions business with Scribner's and an English publisher.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Brooklyn, New York, to Helen Trafford Moore, Asheville, North Carolina, 1932 Aug 18; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Thanks her for a letter and poem; says it is only the second time anyone has written a poem for him and he will always treasure it.] (on Harvard Club stationary)
  - Thomas Wolfe, Brooklyn, to Helen Trafford Moore, Portland, Maine, 1933 Oct 9; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses her work with the deaf; mentions Maxwell Perkins' interest in her work; suggests she put her ideas on paper; recalls her story about a deaf boy; feels it would make a wonderful piece; suggests sending it to Alfred Dashiell of
    Scribner's Magazine
    . ]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Brooklyn, to Helen Trafford Moore, Portland, Maine, 1933 Nov 8; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Promises to speak about her story about deaf people with Alfred Dashiell, which is all he can do in the way of helping to get it published; thinks the piece would be suitable for the series "Life in the United States" which has been featured in
    says Maxwell Perkins would be interested because of his own son's progressing deafness; asks her discreetness about this fact should she ever meet Perkins.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Brooklyn, to Helen Trafford Moore, Portland, Maine, 1934 Jan 30; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Addresses envelope to Miss Helen Trafford Brown; acknowledges her comments about his work; hopes to see her sister and friend, Rose Hildebrand Brown, both from Asheville, when they visit New York; says that the manuscript of [
    Of Time and the River
    ] is with Maxwell Perkins, who is shortening it, adding to it, editing, and rewriting it.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Brooklyn, to Helen Trafford Moore, Portland, Maine, 1934 Apr 11; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Thanks her for cartoon clipping picturing him, which proves his celebrity; reports on progress; says his stories will appear in
    and
    American Mercury
    , that he has received a contract and advance from England and royalties from Germany, that
    The Modern Library
    has secured
    for its Giant's edition, and that he signed agreement for dramatization of
    complains about workload; urges her to read piece in
    plans trip to Vermont with Robert Raynolds. ]
  - Thoms Wolfe, Brooklyn, to Helen Trafford Moore, Asheville, North Carolina, 1934 Jul 30; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Complains about New York's summer weather; is trying to finish [
    ] after 4 years hard work; works with Maxwell Perkins every night; remarks that he could not wait to get to the city and now dreams of a simple life in a tree-shaded cabin with a good strong girl to do the chores; wonders why one is productive one day yet accomplishes nothing on another; comments on her visit to his mother and sister and her compliments on his last story; hopes to vacation in October.]
  - Thoms Wolfe, New York City, to Helen Trafford Moore, Asheville, North Carolina, 1935 Jul 8; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Says he was absent for 4 months; acknowledges her letters and her belief in his work; says that he is happy about the success of his book and wants the next one to be better, if only to prove that he deserves all the good things she and others have said about him.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, [ New York], to [ Scribner's], [ New York], 1936 Jan 17; ANS, 1 p.
    ["Please give Mr. Murdock Dooher, the bearer, the three manuscript items which are included with the typed manuscript in your keeping."]
  - Thomas Wolfe, New York, to Robert [Newton] Linscott, Boston, 1937 Oct 16; ALS, 7 p.
    [Refers to Linscott's letter to him which was written while Wolfe was in Boston; says he could not find him in the phone book and there was no use trying the offices of Houghton Mifflin late on a Saturday afternoon; needs someone to talk to; describes his break with Scribner's; mentions affection for Maxwell Perkins; hints that he is in the market for another publisher; says he can be reached through his agent, Elizabeth Nowell. ]
  - Thomas Wolfe, [ New York], to [ Robert Newton Linscott], Boston, 1937 Dec 20; TLS, 1 p.
    [Points out how hard it was to make "the decision"; regrets disappointing [ Maxwell Perkins] whom he admires so much; appreciates Linscott's interest in his work; feels he has gained a friend, if not a publisher.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, New York, to Barnet B. Ruder, [ New York], 1938 Feb 2; TLS, 2 p.
    [Regards a hearing in Wolfe's suit against [Murdock] Dooher; discusses Ruder's willingness to testify and Ruder's records regarding purchases, which have been examined by Ralph Lum, Wolfe's lawyer; says Belinda Jelliffe and Maxwell Perkins are available to testify.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, New York, to Clifton Fadiman, New York, 1938 May 3; TLS, 1 p.
    [Turns down a proposal concerning contribution to
    Living Philosophies
    , to be published by Simon and Schuster; says his workload is too heavy.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, New York City, to Helen Trafford Moore, Portland, Maine, 1938 May 6; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Says he does not have much news, he is hard work on [
    The Web and the Rock
    ], but plans a vacation after visiting Purdue University on May 19; gives her Elizabeth Nowell's address, as she knows his whereabouts; says he is happy to have a friend who believes in his work.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Hotel Chelsea, New York, to Barnet B. Ruder, New York, 1938 May 12; TLS, 2 p.
    [Reminisces about their "night club orgy" in Harlem; longs to go back with him to do the rhumba at La Conga; says he is hard at work with the book and will "deliver a talk" at Purdue; feels he is not doing well on such occasions, but that $300 will motivate him to do his best; says he is delivering carloads of manuscripts for storage at Harper's until his return from the West; plans to see Colorado, Wyoming, or Yellowstone; talks about some business he has with Ruder regarding Modern First Editions.]
  - Thomas Wolfe, Camp Curry, California, to Barnet B. Ruder, New York, 1938 Jun 22; APCS
    [Writes on postcard of a grizzly bear at Yosemite: "Who's afraid? Regards, T. W."]
  - Elizabeth Nowell, South Dartmouth, Massachusetts, to Helen Trafford Moore, Asheville, North Carolina(redirected from Portland, Maine), 1950 Jun 3; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Identifies herself as Thomas Wolfe's agent from 1933 to his death; says she is under contract with Wolfe's estate and Scribner's to collect and edit his letters; gives several sources to prove her statements, including John Hall Wheelock, editor, Charles Scribner's Sons; asks permission to copy any letters Wolfe wrote her for possible inclusion in a book; mentions 10 letters from Moore to Wolfe; explains legal matters; asks for information about Moore, to be used in the acknowledgment.]
  - Envelope in Mabel Wolfe Wheaton's handwriting to Misses Helen and Elizabeth Moore, Broad and Liberty St., Asheville, N. C., 1955 Dec 15; Envelope
- Photographs
  - Thomas Wolfe, head and shoulders, Photo
    [Four copies, one inscribed by Mabel Wolfe Wheaton. ]
  - Thomas Wolfe, standing in doorway of Mabel Wolfe Wheaton's home, 1937 Jul 19; Photo
    [Inscribed to Helen Trafford Moore from Mabel Wolfe Wheaton. ]
- Miscellaneous
  - Mimeographed copy of radio script of 7 episodes of America Speaks, 1947 Jan-Feb; Script
    [Features sketches from
    16 p., 13 p., 17p., 14 p., 13 p., 13 p., and 14 p.]
  - Typed notes, author unknown, n. d.; Notes
    [Identifying characters from
  - 5 Bookplates, n. d.; Bookplates
    [Picturing Thomas Wolfe in front of his mother's house [Old Kentucky Home] in Asheville, North Carolina. ]